The next relationship between
classes is the so-called aggregation.
This is a relationship that
is somewhat stronger than association.
The interpretation is
as written here:
We say there is aggregation between
classes A and B if instances
of class A contain instances of
class B as parts in some way.
So in
the sense:
There is a whole
that contains multiple parts.
That is first of all
a semantic interpretation, special roles.
Otherwise, it would still
be like an association.
Some relation between A
and B, where references exist.
That could also stand
for whole and parts.
Basically, aggregation is a
notation special case of associations.
Otherwise it has
the same features.
So there are names
of association and aggregation.
There is a reading direction, navigation
directions, multiplicities, roles at the ends.
So a lot of things
are still similar to associations.
It is not somehow forbidden
here, especially by the fact of
an aggregation, that a part belongs
to several or maybe to no whole.
A possible example would
be songs and playlists.
So let's say A would be a class of
playlists and B would be a class of songs.
Of course playlists
contain songs as parts.
But that doesn't mean that a song
can only belong to exactly one playlist.
So being contained
is not so strict
that a song, for example, can only
exist as part of exactly one playlist.
Nevertheless, there is aggregation, so
songs are aggregated to a playlist.
Explicit naming of the
aggregation is often superfluous.
I had said you can name
an aggregation just like you would for
an association and draw
it in the class diagram.
Often this is not necessary, because from
the fact that it is an aggregation,
the nature of
the relationship already follows.
So the relationship might end up
being called "contains" as a name anyway.
Instead of "possesses" one
would perhaps write: "contains".
But this is already clear from
the graphical form of the representation,
because aggregations are
painted differently from associations.
Namely
as follows.
There is a connection
as with the associations also.
But at one end, and specifically at the
end of the whole (that is, what takes the
role of the whole in the
aggregation), there is this unfilled diamond drawn.
An example
would be:
A parking lot
contains several cars.
Here it says
"contains" as name.
But you could
probably save that.
Because by this graphical
form it is already expressed
what kind of relation is
present here, namely an aggregation.
And also the reading direction
is not absolutely necessary there.
Because by the end,
where the diamond is attached,
it is also expressed,
who contains whom here.
So
here:
A parking lot contains
any number of cars.
A car can stand on
a parking lot, or not.
So a car does not exist only as
long as it stands on a parking lot.
A car can also exist
and stand on no parking place.
The role of the whole here
takes over, as said, the parking lot.
The role of the part, in
this part-whole-relationship, takes over the car.
By this "0..1"
multiplicity is expressed that
a car at least never
stands on two parking lots.
While again this multiplicity
should not be given.
Since this is our default multiplicity
anyway, if nothing is written on it.
I could have
left this out.
And then because of something I said
in an earlier video, it would still
be clear for the
scope of the lecture
that there is no restriction on the
number of cars in a parking lot.
What else
could be done?
One could still
specify the navigation direction.
draw a navigation
direction arrow here at
this end to say:
From the parking lot, you can
access the cars that are on it.
A navigation arrow in the
opposite direction would not be possible.
For one thing, there
would be a graphic conflict.
One could not draw
this arrow at all.
On the other hand,
the understanding of aggregation is
that a part knows
to which whole it belongs.
So it
is somehow assumed
that one can determine from the
car also the parking lot containing it.
This is an
example with "0..1".
One might well
have other multiplicities here.
But not
for parking spaces.
It makes no sense that a
car is parked on two parking spaces.
But let's assume that instead of "parking space"
there would be "vehicle fleet" or "car dealer catalog".
Then, of course, a car can be
contained in a car fleet, or in
a car dealer catalog,
and certainly in several.
So an aggregation does not require
that a maximum of 1 is possible.
Different from
the composition.
That's why
I mention this.
In terms
of structural constraints:
How is it now,
if we have a class
diagram with several classes
and in between several aggregations?
Maybe there are
some structural constraints there.
That's where the
situation is like associations.
So it's not
forbidden to have cycles.
It's not forbidden
to have self-references.
It's not forbidden to have
multiple aggregations, or aggregations and associations
mixed, between
the same partners.
It's different
from inheritance.
That
was aggregation.
Now what
about composition?
That was introduced, or briefly mentioned before,
as the strongest of the relationships considered.
So association,
aggregation, and composition.
What is
the understanding here?
A composition, again between
two classes A and B,
also expresses such
a part-whole relationship.
So instances of class A contain
instances of class B as parts.
But in addition to what aggregation
already interprets, here it is required that
the lifetime of the parts
be controlled by the whole.
In the sense that the
parts cannot exist without the whole.
This is not the case
with parking lot and car.
Certainly a parking
lot contains cars.
But that doesn't mean that if the
parking lot is closed or ceases to exist,
therefore all the
cars are destroyed.
With composition, you tend to have this
understanding that the parts are really so
integral to the whole that they
don't exist at all without the whole.
Parts don't have their
own lifetime, so to speak.
That basically
means for implementation:
Parts may (or even must) be deleted
as soon as their associated instance of
class A, that is, the object of class A
of which they are considered a part, is deleted.
And because of this
consideration a part may not
belong to more than one
whole at the same time.
Because then its lifetime would not be
linked to an instance of class A.
So the example with "one song belongs
to several playlists" would not be a composition.
Because the songs don't cease to
exist when a playlist is deleted.
And one song can
also belong to multiple playlists.
And then deleting a playlist
has no effect on the song.
It is still
contained in other playlists.
Playlists-and-songs would not be an
example of composition for this reason.
Naming composition is often
superfluous, similar to aggregation.
Because from the graphical representation, the
character as composition is already obvious.
What we already see when we
compare this with aggregation is that
maybe
the decision
whether to take an aggregation or
a composition is sometimes not very easy.
There is
definitely room for
interpretation, which also depends on what
one wants to express when modeling.
So it may be
that sometimes it makes sense
to use both
aggregation and composition.
Then you have to
choose one or the other.
In some cases
it is also clear.
Later on, we will see
a few criteria listed as mnemonics.
These are basically the same as
the two criteria that are used here
to decide whether something is really
a composition and not just an aggregation.
But first, let's take a
look at the graphical representation.
So for a composition, you take
a similar representation as for aggregation.
But now this
diamond is filled in.
That's the difference between aggregation and
composition, how this diamond looks here.
Example:
A company consists of
any number of departments.
"Consists of" is
the composition here.
The company
is the whole.
The departments
are the parts.
There can be
any number of them.
The interpretation here is that the
departments just cease to exist as
soon as the
company ceases to exist.
If the company is dissolved,
then these departments are also dissolved.
And a department cannot belong
to several companies at the same
time (just like a song can belong
to several playlists at the same time).
That makes no
sense in this constellation.
Therefore composition and
not only aggregation.
Regarding navigation arrows, the
same applies as before:
You could still draw a
navigation arrow here in this direction.
In the opposite direction it is
not necessary and also not possible,
because that would
give a graphic conflict.
And since one assumes anyway that the parts
know in each case what their whole is.
Here one could
write a multiplicity again.
However, with composition, the
choice is actually very limited.
There can be only
the multiplicity "0..1" or "1".
All other
multiplicities are not
allowed for compositions at
the end of the whole.
The most common multiplicity
would be exactly 1.
In this case it is
usually not written at all.
This is
then the situation:
A part belongs
to exactly one whole,
and this always, and cannot belong also
temporarily for example times to no whole.
We will discuss another
case of compositions, where
"0..1" also makes
sense, at least temporarily.
So also these would be
criteria, which can be used
to distinguish between
aggregation and composition.
If you can imagine a
multiplicity of more than 1
at this end, then it is
not a composition, but an aggregation.
Moreover, it should be
noted that this requirement (to
belong to at most one whole)
is stronger than just the multiplicities indicate.
So a part could
potentially, at least at the
class level, be in
compositional relation to multiple wholes.
There could be two classes to which a
class is in compositional relation as a part.
Then it would not matter
what is at the ends here.
Even if there stands "0..1" in each case, it
may not be nevertheless that the part belongs at the
same time to a whole of the one
class and a whole of the other class.
You really have to be careful
what this "belongs to exactly", or in
the case of 0..1 "to
at most one whole" means.
But we will
also discuss that.
First I would like to
quote the promised mnemonic sentences.
They are from one of the books I
had shown you in the review of literature.
This English-language book
on object-oriented design.
Those are ultimately in English the things
that I expressed on the slides as well.
So kind of an association
as this vaguest form of relationship.
Which kind of represents when
anything needs to be stored as
data and there needs to be
a relationship between objects of two classes.
Examples
would be:
Ownership.
Control of objects of one
class over objects of another class.
General
relationships.
"Being a part of something" can also
be an association, but is more likely to
be captured as
an aggregation right away.
Being a
member of something.
Some associations also lent themselves to
the library class example that came up
last week or the week
before, such as borrowing books.
When shouldn't
you use associations?
For one thing, when it comes
to relationships that correspond to a hierarchy.
I mentioned that
at the beginning, too.
Then you would either have
inheritance hierarchies or rather aggregation/composition.
And it has to be
somehow a relationship that is persistent.
That is, that is not
only very temporarily necessary when executing
maybe exactly one
operation or one method.
In that case it would simply be possible to
pass the target object as a parameter to the method.
An association would be made
if it is a relationship that
survives the execution
of a single operation.
So anything that should be
stored permanently over the objects.
What
was aggregation?
A special kind of association
where it's about somehow objects of
class A being composed
of objects of class B.
If somehow there is a part-whole relationship
between the objects of classes A and B.
That
was aggregation.
Composition was
even stronger.
There is the requirement that each instance
of this part class can belong to
only one instance of the whole
class, and cannot exist without it.
The part can only exist
as part of the whole.
These were the criteria I had also
discussed on the previous slides, just summarized
here again in
a compact way.